Guide to the Cooper Medical College Collection
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Cooper Medical College collection
1857-1974
1857-1894
SC0923
Stanford University
0.75 Linear feet
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Biographical/Historical note
The Medical Department of the University of the Pacific was the first medical school on the West Coast, founded in San Francisco in 1858 by Dr. Elias Samuel Cooper. Following the death of Dr. Cooper in 1862, the program was suspended. In 1864, Dr. Hugh Huger Toland founded Toland Medical College in San Francisco, which later became the medical department of the University of California. By 1872 the Medical Department of the University of the Pacific was reorganized as the Medical College of the Pacific in affiliation with University (City) College. In 1882 Dr. Levi Cooper Lane generously donated a state of the art building to the medical school and the name of the school was subsequently changed from the Medical College of the Pacific to Cooper Medical College in honor of Dr. Lane's uncle, Dr. Elias Samuel Cooper. In 1908, Dr. Lane granted permission for the equipment and properties of Cooper Medical College to be transferred to Stanford University. Instruction by Stanford University began in 1909 and continued in San Francisco until 1959, at which time the Stanford School of Medicine opened on the Stanford campus.
Scope and Contents note
The Cooper Medical College collection consists primarily of ephemeral material such as commencement invitations, programs, and addresses from Cooper Medical College and its predecessors, the Medical College of the Pacific, and Toland Medical College. Also included are several printed lectures from the Medical College of the Pacific, 1861-1879, annual reports, medical publications, faculty handbooks, clippings, and an alumni directory.
Access Terms
Cooper Medical College.; Cooper, Elias Samuel, 1820-1862.; Lane, Levi Cooper, 1833-1902.; Medical College of the Pacific (San Francisco, Calif.); Toland Medical College.; University of the Pacific. Medical Dept.; Medicine--California; Medicine--History; Medicine--Study and teaching--California --Stanford.
Collection Contents
- Collection items
  - Toland Medical College
    - Toland Medical College-Opening Address, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Toland Medical College-Valedictory Address, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Toland Medical College-Annual Announcement of Lectures, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Toland Medical College-History from: Thompson, William Benbow. The Story of the Professorship of Obstetrics at the University of California. Reprinted from: Portland, Or: Western Journal of Surgery Pub. Co, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical College of the Pacific
    - Announcement of the Medical Department of the University of the Pacific
      The present pamphlet indicates that while the school was established in 1858, it did not begin normal operation until the spring of the following year. "The regular Annual Course of Lectures in this Institution will commence on the first Monday in May, 1859, and be continued for eighteen weeks" (p. 8). The pamphlet also includes a brief outline of the courses offered and a schedule of fees.
    - Medical College of the Pacific-Lectures, 1861-1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Medical College of the Pacific-Annual Announcements, 1872-1882 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Medical College of the Pacific-Commencement Programs, 1871-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cooper, Elias Samuel-publications, addresses, biographical, 1856-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Elias S. Cooper, founder of California's (and the West Coast's) first medical school, came to San Francisco in May 1855 and immediatelyembarked on an ambitious program to advance the status of medicine in the state. He not only established his own medical and surgical practice in the city (which he promoted vigorously, to the dismay of some of his rivals), but also began his own private medical teaching program), agitated for improvements in the teaching of anatomy, helped to found both the San Francisco County Medico-Chirurgical Association and the California State Medical Society, began publishing the prestigious Pacific Medical and Surgical Journal, and in the fall of 1858 founded California's first medical school, attached to the University of the Pacific. The medical school's faculty originally consisted of Cooper and six others; Cooper's nephew, Levi Cooper Lane, joined the faculty in 1859. Cooper served as professor of anatomy and surgery at the school from its inception until his death eight years later. After Cooper's death the school went into decline, being eclipsed by the foundation in 1864 of the rival Toland Medical College, ancestor of the University of California's medical school. In 1870 Cooper's school was revived by Levi Cooper Lane and Henry Gibbons; in 1882 it was renamed Cooper Medical College after its founder. After several decades of independent existence, Cooper Medical College was acquired by Stanford University; Stanford University'sSchool of Medicine thus can trace its ancestry back to the first medical school founded on the West Coast.
  - Lane, Levi Cooper-dissertation, publications, 1876-1891, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Thorne, W. S.-"Report on Surgery", 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cooper Medical College
    - Cooper Medical College-Annual Announcement, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cooper Medical College-Annual Report (Morse Dispensary), 1884-1890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cooper Medical College-Annual Report (Dispensary), 1891-1893 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cooper Medical College-Annual Report of Clinics, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cooper Medical College-Commencement Invitations and Programs, 1883-1912 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cooper Medical College-Commencement Addresses, 1884-1888 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cooper Medical College-Commencement Addresses, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Cooper Medical College-Commencement Addresses, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cooper Medical College-Commencement Addresses, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Cooper Medical College-Announcement of Lectures, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cooper Medical College- Anatomical and Surgical Lectures (advertisement); To the Medical Profession (advertisement)., 1856, 01858 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cooper Medical College-Building-Dedication, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cooper Medical College-Building: Shuman, Ronald. Portraits: The Cooper Medical Building, the Lane Hospital Building. San Francisco: Pacific Medical Center, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cooper Medical College-Rules for the Government of the Faculty of Cooper Medical College, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cooper Medical College-Stanford University, and J. H. Wythe. Faculty of the Cooper Medical College, Successor to the Medical College of the Pacific, San Francisco, 1882-1912. [Palo Alto]: Stanford University, School of Medicine, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cooper Medical College-Letter to Alumni, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cooper Medical College-Alumni Directory, 1859-1912. San Francisco, CA: Cooper Medical College, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Cooper Medical College-Barkan, Hans. Cooper Medical College, Founded by Levi Cooper Lane; an Historical Sketch. San Francisco, Ca: Stanford Medical Bulletin, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cooper Medical College-Clippings, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)